All right, בוקר טוב. boker tov. Yes, today's דף daf is דף
ג', daf gimmel, and just to review what we did yesterday in
סוכה, Sukkah, we introduced a couple of major themes. We're dealing with
the discussion of the height of twenty אמות, amot, but some of
the important themes we introduced was the question of a סוכה sukkah
temporary dwelling,
which was one reason given for the need for it not to
be too tall. The other issue that we introduced was the idea,
excuse me, I should have started by saying that the first major
point is that the concept of סוכה sukkah is primarily defined by
סכך, sechach,
and that was clear that a number of the אמוראים amoraim when
they explain the problem of being too high, it was the סכך
sechach being too high and focus on פסוקים pesukim that mention the
word סוכה sukkah and סוכה sukkah is by nature taken to mean
the סכך. sechach. And so one of the issues was the question
about permanence versus temporary, and the other was the idea of being
able to see the סכך, sechach, and the importance of understanding the
significance of the סכך, sechach, maybe to some degree למען ידעו דורותיכם,
lema'an yedu doroteichem, but to see the סכך. sechach. And the third
was the issue of what do you call it,
of of סכך sechach's ability to provide shade, not just according to
one opinion to have the intrinsic quality of blocking out the sunlight,
but to in effect give shade to the סוכה, sukkah, and therefore
if it was too high, that would be a problem. And yet
the issue of interestingly the גמרא Gemara says that the question of
temporary dwelling is not defined by building material, you can make a
brick סוכה. sukkah.
But תוספות Tosafot raise the important question, and the גמרא'ס Gemara's focusing
on the question about the dimensions, but תוספות Tosafot raise the important
question about can the סכך sechach be so permanent that it is
defined as your house? And תוספות'ס Tosafot's conclusion was that it could.
One definition of תוספות Tosafot for the סכך sechach being permanent that
it would no longer be considered temporary would be that rain would
be impossible for rain to get through. Dov was mentioning a second
ago, there is also this idea being able to see the stars
which is I believe based on ירושלמי Yerushalmi or something. Anyway, it's
not certainly not a strict requirement, תוספות'ס Tosafot's focus was about the
rain getting through. We also raised the issue about you know just
the permanent nature of a סכך, sechach, nailed in with nails and
planks and the whole thing and plaster. So presumably again another example
where maybe that's not quantified, but the identity of a סוכה sukkah
very much tied up in the סכך. sechach. So we continue now
at the bottom of ב' עמוד ב' bet amud bet where it
says
בשלמא, bishlama, three lines from the bottom. And we're now going to
try to prove which of these explanations is the correct one for
the problem of the height based on this story with Queen הלני
Hilni who sat in a סוכה sukkah higher than twenty אמות. amot.
This was the proof that רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda gave the Rabbis
to which the Rabbis retorted and said that's not a proof, she
was a woman and she was exempt. And he said back, yeah,
but she had sons, and as the גמרא Gemara sort of elaborated,
at least her sons were obligated in rabbinically from the חינוך chinuch
perspective. So let's take a look. בשלמא למאן דאמר בשאין דפנות מגיעות
לסכך. bishlama leman de'amar beshein defanot megi'ot lasechach. So this works according
to the approach that says that the whole problem of the height
is only when the the walls don't reach the סכך. sechach. Because
if the issue is will you will you see the סכך, sechach,
so if the walls reach the סכך, sechach, your eyes will be
drawn up to the intersection of the walls and the roof. So
the only debate was when the walls didn't reach the סכך, sechach,
and but if the walls reached the סכך sechach it could be
as high as you want. So that works because obviously this case
of הלני Hilni was the case a case that's relevant to the
debate.
גוד אסיק gudd assik doesn't help? גוד אסיק gudd assik helps to
say you have a wall, but here the question is the problem
of will you see the סכך. sechach. So that's a real a
question of reality. So the גמרא Gemara says דרכה של מלכה לישב
בסוכה שאין דפנות מגיעות לסכך. darkah shel malka leishev besukkah she'ein defanot
megi'ot lasechach. So it would be normal, it's totally understandable that she
was sitting in a סוכה, sukkah, you know, it's very fancy סוכה
sukkah with built-in air conditioning that had the walls not reaching the
סכך sechach so could be getting in a nice breeze.
משום
אוירא, mishum avira, in order to get some air circulation going on.
Top of ג' עמוד א'. gimmel amud aleph. אלא למאן דאמר בסוכה
קטנה מחלוקת. ella leman de'amar besukkah ketana machloket. But according to the
approach that the problem is that the סכך sechach won't provide shade,
and therefore the problem is only with a very small סוכה, sukkah,
because therefore the סכך sechach covers a small area, and if it's
too high it won't provide shade. But if it's a larger סוכה
sukkah and a larger area, then it's not a problem, even high
סכך sechach will provide shade. So according to that approach that their
whole debate was in a small סוכה, sukkah, how could they have
been debating the case of הלני? Hilni? וכי דרכה של מלכה לישב
בסוכה קטנה? vechi darkah shel malka leishev besukkah ketana? Would a would
a queen sit in such a tiny סוכה, sukkah, four by four
אמות? amot? Very reasonable question. So how could you say that that's
their debate? Look at the you know they're debating הלני Hilni and
clearly she must have been sitting in a big סוכה. sukkah. So
אמר רבה בר רב אדא amar Rabba bar Rav Adda lo. לא
נצרכה אלא לסוכה העשויה קיטוניות קיטוניות. lo nitzrecha ela l'sukkah asuyah kitoniyot
kitoniyot. It's a סוכה Sukkah that's made with little compartments. So yeah,
maybe it's a huge סוכה, Sukkah, but there are private little eating
compartments that you go into and eat in private and therefore the
issue as those halachically, even if it's really one big structure and
it's like a building, a building has a big structure with rooms.
So even if it's technically true that it's a big structure from
the outside, halachically, if inside you're sitting in a chamber that has
four walls and an inner chamber, that's the סוכה. Sukkah. The סוכה
Sukkah isn't judged by the big thing. The סוכה Sukkah is the
space you're sitting in surrounded by walls. And therefore the סכך s'chach
directly above it would be small and would be too high and
not able to provide shade below.
Those walls would also have to go all the way up to
the סכך? s'chach?
No, don't confuse it. The הלכה halakhah
is for סוכה Sukkah to be כשרה kosher the walls don't have
to go to the סכך. s'chach. The issue of walls go to
סכך s'chach was according to one opinion that if the walls reach
the סכך s'chach it could be as high as you want. Right.
So this is the other opinion. This is the opinion that says
that the issue is not seeing the סכך, s'chach, the issue is
the סכך s'chach practical providing of shade, and it's only a problem,
it's only debated when you're talking about a small סוכה. Sukkah. So
how could we be having a small סוכה Sukkah here? So according
to this it doesn't matter if you get to סכך s'chach or
not. Question is, how big is the area of the סכך? s'chach?
So it says since how could the queen be in a small
סוכה? Sukkah? It's a big סוכה, Sukkah, but there are little separate
little rooms and
therefore that's why she was technically in a small סוכה. Sukkah. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says וכי דרכה של מלכה לישב בסוכה העשויה
קיטוניות קיטוניות? V'chi darkah shel malkah leishav b'sukkah asuyah kitoniyot kitoniyot? Would
the queen sit in a סוכה Sukkah that's all tiny little chambers?
Like wall, like I
presumably it's imagining
that you go into your compartment, there's no general larger sitting room,
so the whole thing is just has tiny little chambers for people.
אמר רב אשי, Amar Rav Ashi, לא נצרכה אלא לקיטוניות שבה. lo
nitzrecha ela l'kitoniyot shebah. No, it really is a nice big outer
room that everybody can sit, but then it also has little side
chambers and she was sitting in a little side chamber. Now that's
still a little funny. Wouldn't the queen be sitting in the larger
room? Maybe she was sitting in the larger room to greet guests,
but when she would go eat, she would go eat in private.
Anyway, and that's the case.
Now
רש"י Rashi says רבנן סברי בנה בסוכה מעליא הוה יתבי. rabbanan savri
b'nah b'sukkah ma'alya hava yatvi. So the rabbis figured okay, it doesn't
prove anything. She's eating in private and presumably her sons would eat
in the large dining room. And therefore it's not a problem that
the sons
even though the סוכה Sukkah is tall, the sons are in a
large סוכה Sukkah and this is the approach that a large סוכה
Sukkah there's not a problem with height because the סכך s'chach provides
shade. רבי
יהודה סבר בנה גבה הוה יתבי. Rabbi Yehuda savar b'nah gabah hava
yatvi.
No, the kids were with her in one of the tiny little
rooms. ואפילו הכי לא אמרו ליה דבר v'afillu hachi lo amru leih
davar and they didn't say anything, so that's his proof. Everybody was
in a tiny little room and therefore if it's small there's a
problem of the height, that's where it's debated the height, because that's
the problem of the סכך s'chach providing shade. ורבי יהודה V'Rabbi Yehuda
says they didn't say anything to her, so you see it's really
not a problem. Okay, so what we have to do is, since
according to one approach the problem of the סכך s'chach being too
high is a problem that it won't provide shade and that the
גמרא Gemara qualified and said is only a problem if it's a
very small סכך, s'chach, a small סוכה, Sukkah, how could they have
been debating the הלני Helni case? Wouldn't it obviously have been a
large סוכה? Sukkah? And the גמרא's Gemara's answer is no, she actually
was sitting in a small chamber and that's why they could debate
it. And the question about can't you bring a proof where the
sons were and doesn't that prove that they were sitting in a
that it was an okay סוכה? Sukkah? The rabbis say no, the
sons were sitting in the big section and again nobody would debate
if it's a big סוכה. Sukkah. It's as far as the small
section where we debate that already they said is a what do
you call it, it would only have been her. By the way
רש"י Rashi says how could רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda have said that
according to this re-read of the ברייתא Braita that all the kids
were with her in a little section? How could all the kids
fit in a tiny little section? If it's ארבע אמות arba amot
by ארבע אמות arba amot maybe, but if it's like שבעה טפחים
shiva tefachim by שבעה טפחים shiva tefachim which is another approach, certainly
not, how could they fit? And even ארבע אמות arba amot by
ארבע אמות arba amot how could they all fit in a tiny
little section? And there were seven of them. So תוספות Tosafot says
it's not a problem. תוספות Tosafot says because, and this is an
important idea for סוכה, Sukkah, to be the minimum size it's not
sufficient that it has the minimum area. It has to have both
the right width and length. So תוספות Tosafot says you could have
had a section, a room that's three and a half אמות amot
wide and twenty אמות amot long and that's not a minimum סוכה
Sukkah because in one dimension it's not the minimum length. So therefore
all seven sons could have sat. And maybe also in that case
we would say the סכך s'chach wouldn't provide. shade. In order for
the סכך s'chach to provide shade, it would have to be four
אמות amot in each direction. It's not enough that it's very long;
it would have to go the minimum in both directions. Yes.
Yes, the picture book indicates it's not so much a chamber, but
sort of an extra
indication.
Well, that's because it's going to the second answer that there's a
large dining room and then there's a chamber off side of it.
That doesn't matter. The only difference is whether there would be a
door there or not. If there would be a door, you'd call
it a chamber. Okay, it's basically the same point. All right. So
that's what we basically have said, different approaches to the debate of
twenty אמות, amot, they lead to different limitations or different you know
cases in which it's a problem. Maybe it's only a problem if
the walls don't get to the סכך, s'chach, maybe it's only a
problem in a small סוכה. sukkah. And tries to test that theory
out by this case by הילני Hilni which was debated. So let's
take a look. Now the גמרא, Gemara, because we're talking about four
by four, or ראשו ורובו ושולחאנו, rosho verubo veshulchano, and we raised
yesterday that question about what's the minimum size of a סוכה, sukkah,
now it's important to shift gear. We're putting aside for now the
question about the twenty אמה amah height and what it's based on.
We're now going to focus on the issue that was came up
incidentally, which was what is the minimum size of a סוכה. sukkah.
So you have a total normal סוכה, sukkah, six feet tall, eight
feet tall, we're not talking about height. That doesn't matter. We're talking
about a different question now. What is the
minimum size of a סוכה? sukkah? So let's take a look. So
אמר שמואל בר יצחק. amar Shmuel bar Yitzchak. So said שמואל בר
יצחק, Shmuel bar Yitzchak, הלכה צריכה כדי מחזקת ראשו ורובו ושולחאנו. halacha
tsricha kidei machzeket rosho verubo veshulchano. The הלכה halacha is that a
סוכה sukkah has to be able to fit your head, your body,
and your table, meaning it's not four by four אמות, amot, which
לפי lefee is the position of רבי Rebbe as the minimum size.
It's much smaller size. Your head, most your body—again the reason we
say most your body is because you're reclining, so you have to
get in not just your head but like you know half of
your height, okay, and your table, which is about seven טפחים tfachim
by seven טפחים, tfachim, which is about we say seven and a
bit, so it's about what like something like about two feet by
two feet. Okay, so that makes sense, two feet from your waist
to the top of your head. Again it's also your head is
probably propped up a little bit so... Well no, but your head
is not totally like this, your head is a little bit like
this, it's probably a little bit probably a little bit from your
waist to your shoulders or something. Anyway, so okay so that's the
צד. tsad. So אמר ליה רבי אבא, amar lei Rabbi Abba, so
first of all it's rejecting the opinion of רבי Rebbe that we'll
see later says four by four אמות. amot. So said רבי אבא,
Rabbi Abba, כמאן? keman? Who's that going like? כבית שמאי? kebet Shammai?
Are you going like בית שמאי? Bet Shammai? אמר ליה, amar lei,
אלא כמאן? ela keman? He said back then, yeah and who else
would I be going like? So so what does this mean בית
שמאי? Bet Shammai? If you take a look it's important to turn
for a moment to כ"ח עמוד א' chaf chet amud alef and
to read the משנה mishna there because this is all in reference
to the rest of the עמוד amud is going to
be in reference to the משנה mishna
on כ"ח עמוד א',
chaf chet amud alef, 28a, so let's look over there
at the משנה mishna at the bottom of the page. Okay, מי
שהיה ראשו... mi shehaya rosho... Yeah. Yeah. So this is the idea
of the of the minimum size of the סוכה sukkah but you'll
see it's a little confusing and you'll also see an interesting parallel
to what we just read about הילני המלכה Hilni hamalka and debating
what actually happened. מי שהיה ראשו ורובו בסוכה, mi shehaya rosho verubo
besukkah, somebody who's head and the majority of his body was in
the סוכה sukkah ושולחנו בתוך הבית, veshulchano betoch habayit, and the table
was in the house. בית שמאי פוסלין, ובית הלל מכשירין, Beit Shammai
poslin u’Beit Hillel makhshirin. and בית הלל Bet Hillel says that it's
כשר. kosher. אמרו להן בית הלל לבית שמאי, amru lehei Bet Hillel
leBet Shammai, בית הלל Bet Hillel said to בית שמאי: Bet Shammai:
לא כך היה מעשה lo kach haya maaseh שהלכו זקני בית שמאי
וזקני בית הלל לבקר את יוחנן בן החורנית, shehalchu ziknei Bet Shammai
veziknei Bet Hillel levaker et Yochanan ben haChoranis, wasn't there the following
story that the elders of the houses of שמאי Shammai and הלל
Hillel went to visit יוחנן בן החורנית? Yochanan ben haChoranis? ומצאוהו שהיה
יושב ראשו ורובו בסוכה, umatsuhu shehaya yoshev rosho verubo besukkah, he was
sitting, him and the majority of him was within the סוכה sukkah
ושולחנו בתוך הבית, veshulchano betoch habayit, and his table was in the
house. ולא אמרו לו דבר, velo amru lo davar, they didn't say
anything to him. So you see, the table can be in the
house. אמרו להם בית שמאי, amru lahem Bet Shammai, so בית שמאי
Bet Shammai retorted back: משם ראיה? misham raya? You want to bring
a proof from there? אף הם אמרו לו. af hem amru lo.
That wasn't the whole story. They said to them, they said to
him, maybe at least the בית שמאי Bet Shammai said to him,
אם כן היית נוהג לא קיימת מצוות סוכה מימיך, im ken hayita
noheg lo kiyamta mitzvat sukkah miyamecha, hey buddy, right now, just the
parenthesis is, if you're sick you don't really maybe it doesn't necessarily
mean he's sick, they went to visit him. Okay I just threw
in ביקור חולים bikur cholim so that, it says לבקר. levaker. But
okay so they said if you if this is what you used
to do maybe you've not only have you not done סוכה sukkah
today but you actually have never done סוכה sukkah in your life
if if this is your practice to have the the table inside
the house. So yeah that is the story that his table's in
the house but the story was not they didn't say anything to
him the story was actually there they were they were paying him
a nice little visit and then you know when you go pay
somebody a visit you point out to them all the problems in
their סוכה. sukkah. So that's what actually happened. Okay so what we
see is a debate of בית הלל בית שמאי Bet Hillel Bet
Shammai now here's the problem the משנה mishna makes it sound like
it's not dealing with the size of the סוכה. sukkah. The משנה
mishna makes it sound like the סוכה sukkah is however big the
סוכה sukkah is it's just a reality that you're keeping your table
in the house. Now imagine here table does not necessarily even mean
serving table it's like a tray that you have the food on
that you eat off of. It's basically like saying your... plate. So
there you are, you're sitting in your סוכה sukkah and your plate
with the food is in your house. So what you do is
you go out of your סוכה, sukkah, you
take another slice
of the meat, you come back and you sit and you eat
it.
Then you go back into the house, you take another slice of
the potato,
and you come back and you eat it. So you can understand
why you would not want somebody to say that they could sit
in a סוכה sukkah that way, because next thing they know, they'll
be sitting in the house, right? So therefore, that's the debate. What's
the story when your שולחן shulchan is in the house and you're
in the סוכה? sukkah? Well, that's what, that's what you should imagine
it. The שולחן shulchan is the tray that has the food. It's
not that I, I imagine the סוכה sukkah right up against the
house. So it could be against the house, so fine. You don't
have to get off of your seat, but you're going like this,
and then you're turning around here, and but still next thing you
know, you're still stretching into the house to get your food. Fine.
So anyway, so then the point is that seems to be one
question: do we let you eat with keeping your food in the
house and having to go and get your food? That's one issue,
but the גמרא Gemara understands it that it's also a debate of
the minimum size of a סוכה. sukkah. Does a סוכה sukkah have
to be able to contain your שולחן shulchan or not? בית הלל
Beit Hillel says I don't care if your שולחן shulchan is in
the house, says therefore the minimum size doesn't have to be able
to contain a שולחן. shulchan. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says I need
your שולחן shulchan to be with you, says the minimum size has
to be able to contain a שולחן. shulchan. So is the minimum
size of a סוכה sukkah ראשו ורובו rosho v’rubo or is it
ראשו ורובו ושולחנו? rosho v’rubo v’shulchano? So does it also have to
be able to fit for your שולחן? shulchan? So he said, if
you're saying the minimum size is your head and your body and
your שולחן, shulchan, who are you going like, בית שמאי? Beit Shammai?
And he said, yeah, who else? Okay, which is a funny who
else, because you normally don't פוסק posken like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai.
איכא דאמרי, ikka d’amri, some say, אמר רבי אבא דאמר לך מני,
amar Rabbi Abba d’amar lach manni, so רבי אבא Rabbi Abba said
to רב שמואל בר יצחק, Rav Shmuel bar Yitzchak, who told you
you could do this, who told you this position of ראשו ורובו
ושולחנו? rosho v’rubo v’shulchano? אמר ליה, amar lei, he said that בית
שמאי היא. Beit Shammai hi. Yeah, I know what you're asking. It's
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. ולא תזוז מינה, v’lo tazuz minnah, and but
don't move from it. This is the הלכה. halacha. I'm sorry, here
we פוסק posken like בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. Okay. מתקיף לה רב
נחמן בר יצחק, matkif la Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, רב נחמן בר
יצחק Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak asked, ממאי דבית שמאי ובית הלל בסוכה
קטנה פליגי? mimmay d’Beit Shammai u’Beit Hillel b’sukkah ketannah pligi? What makes
you say that בית שמאי Beit Shammai and בית הלל Beit Hillel
debate a small סוכה, sukkah, meaning what how where you get this
idea that they're debating the minimum size? דילמא בסוכה גדולה פליגי, dilma
b’sukkah gedolah pligi, maybe they're debating a case of a nice big
normal sized סוכה? sukkah? וכגון דיתבי אפומא דמטולתא, u’k’gon d’yatbi a’pumma d’metulta,
and this is the way דב Dov was describing it, you're sitting
there right at the opening, the doorway of your סוכה. sukkah. מטולתא
metulta is the Aramaic word for סוכה. sukkah. Don't forget it, it'll
come up a lot. ושולחנו בתוך הבית, v’shulchano b’toch ha’bayit, and your
שולחן shulchan is in the house, and your house directly opens into
your סוכה. sukkah. דבית שמאי סברי גזרינן שמא יימשך אחר שולחנו. d’Beit
Shammai savri gazrinan shema yimashekh achar shulchano. בית שמאי Beit Shammai says
it's a גזירה. gezeirah. It's not a question of a biblical minimum
size. It's a rabbinic problem of do we let you do this
or not. בית שמאי Beit Shammai is afraid if we let you
do this, next thing you know you'll be eating inside the house.
ובית הלל סברי לא גזרינן, u’Beit Hillel savri lo gazrinan, we're not
concerned and we don't make an edict. ודיקא נמי, v’dayka nami, and
actually it can be inferred by the word, by a close read
of the words, דקתני מי שהיה ראשו ורובו בסוכה ושולחנו בתוך הבית.
d’katani mi she’hayah rosho v’rubo b’sukkah v’shulchano b’toch ha’bayit. So it describes
the scenario, not what the size is, but it describes the scenario
that in fact the שולחן shulchan is in the house. בית שמאי
פוסלין Bet Shammai poslin, ובית הלל מכשירין. ubet Hillel machshirin, ואי סלקא
דעתך, v’i salka da’atach, if it's like you think, that they're debating
the minimum size, not the presence of the שולחן, shulchan, מחזקת ואינה
מחזקת מיבעי ליה. makhziket v’einah makhziket mibba’ei lei. It should have said
a סוכה sukkah that can contain your body and your שולחן shulchan
or only your body without your שולחן. shulchan. It should have described
the capacity of the סוכה sukkah rather than the scenario that the
שולחן shulchan is in the house. Since it's talking about not the
capacity but about the scenario of the שולחן shulchan in the house,
clearly they're debating can you do that act and do we make
a גזירה gezeirah and not a question of a minimum size. So
therefore, minimum size, who knows what the minimum size is? So the
גמרא Gemara says like this, ובסוכה קטנה לא פליגי? u’b’sukkah ketannah lo
pligi? Do you mean to tell me that they're not also debating
the minimum size? והתניא, ve’hatanya, we taught in the ברייתא, braita, מחזקת
ראשו ורובו ושולחנו כשירה. makhziket rosho v’rubo v’shulchano k’shira. If it contains
your head, your body, and your שולחן, shulchan, it’s kosher. רבי יהודה
אומר עד שיהא בה ארבע אמות על ארבע אמות, Rabbi Yehuda omer
ad she’yehe bah arba amot al arba amot, four by four אמות.
amot. So that clearly is a debate of dimensions. It's a debate
of the minimum size. And that's רבי, Rabbi, a four by four
אמות, amot, and בית הלל, Beit Hillel, בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, that’s
whatever, and the other position that's ראשו ורובו ושולחנו. rosho v’rubo v’shulchano.
Fine. דתניא אידך, d’tanya idakh, but we have another ברייתא braita that
says, רבי אומר כל סוכה שאין בה ארבע אמות על ארבע אמות
פסולה, Rabbi omer kol sukkah she’ein bah arba amot al arba amot
psula, any סוכה sukkah that's not four by four is invalid. וחכמים
אומרים אפילו אינה מחזקת אלא ראשו ורובו כשירה, va’chachamim omrim afillu einah
makhziket ella rosho v’rubo k’shira, it only has to be able to
contain your head and your body. ואילו שולחנו לא קתני, v’illu shulchano
lo katani, but the word שולחן shulchan is not in that ברייתא.
braita. So basically what it's saying is is that we have two
ברייתות. braitot. In both ברייתות braitot רבי Rabbi says the minimum size
is four by four, but what What's the opposing opinion? The one
ברייתא braisa: *braita* it says it has to be the minimum size
is your head, your body, and your table, and the other ברייתא
*braita* that says your head and your body. So clearly there's two
opinions out there whether
a סוכה sukkah *sukkah* has to contain your table or not.
And it makes sense to assume that that maps onto the debate
of בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel* and בית שמאי Beit Shammai
*Beit Shammai* in the משנה Mishnah *Mishna* about the scenario of the
table being in the house. That בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beit Shammai*
is concerned with your table not being in your סוכה sukkah *sukkah*,
so he'd be concerned with the סוכה sukkah *sukkah* not being able
to contain your table. And בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beit Hillel* is
not concerned with it being in the house, and he's not concerned
with it having that capacity. So in the ברייתות *braitot* we have
the language of מחזיק *machezik*? Exactly, and it's clearly the ברייתא'ס *braita's*
minimum size. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says okay, ואילו שולחנו לא
קתני *v'ilu shulchano lo katani*. קשיין אהדדי *kashyan adadi*, it's a contradiction
of the ברייתות *braitot*. אלא לאו שמע Shema מינה הא בית שמאי
Beit Shammai הא בית הלל Beit Hillel *ela lav shema mina ha
Beit Shammai ha Beit Hillel*, it must be one of the... the
one that says you have to contain the table is בית שמאי
Beit Shammai *Beit Shammai*, the one that says it doesn't is בית
הלל Beit Hillel, *Beit Hillel*. אמר מר amar mar, זוטרא *amar mar
zutra*, מר זוטרא *mar zutra* says מתניתין נמי דייקא *matnitin nami dika*.
There's a part of the משנה Mishnah, *Mishna* you were trying to
infer from some of the language of the משנה Mishnah *Mishna*, בשולחנו
בתוך הבית *bishulchano betoch habayit*, it was describing a scenario, it wasn't
describing the dimensions. You were inferring that it was talking about a
large סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. Well, I will tell you that a close
reading of some of the words of the משנה mishna: *Mishna* makes
it clear that we're also talking about the minimum size. What's the
evidence from the משנה mishna: *Mishna*? מדקתני בית שמאי Beit Shammai. פוסלין
ובית הלל מכשירין machshirin *midikatani Beit Shammai poslin u-Beit Hillel machshirin*. It
says בית שמאי Beit Shammai *Beit Shammai* invalidate and בית bayis הלל
*Beit Hillel* says it's kosher. Now saying פסול *pasul* and כשר *kasher*
is normally how you describe an object. The object's invalid, the object
is kosher. Okay, maybe you could say the מעשה מצווה *ma'aseh mitzvah*
is פסול *pasul*, but normally not. Normally פסול *pasul* means the object.
So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says it sounds like they're talking about
whether the סוכה sukkah *sukkah* is כשר *kasher* or פסול *pasul*. ואי
איתא *v'im itai*, if the whole debate was only about whether rabbinically
we allow this or not, בית שמאי Beit Shammai אימא לא יצא
lo yatza, ובית הלל אימא יצא מבעי ליה *Beit Shammai eima lo
yatza u-Beit Hillel eima yatza miba'ei lei*. It should have said בית
שמאי Beit Shammai *Beit Shammai* says you didn't fulfill your obligation. So
actually the משנה *Mishna* has contradictory language. Some of the language of
the משנה *Mishna* says invalid, valid, invalid, which makes it sound like
we're talking about the סוכה sukkah *sukkah*, and some talk about a
scenario that your table's in your house, not about a question of
size of the סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. So ואלא קשיא מה שהיה *ve-ela
kashya mi-shaya*? But how do you reconcile the focus on the object
of the סוכה sukkah *sukkah* with the other part of the משנה
*Mishna* that describes the scenario of the act of eating and how
the eating is being done? So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says לעולם
בתרתי פליגי *le-olam bitarti pligi*. You know what? You're right. We have
to assume that there's two debates going on here. פליגי בסוכה קטנה
פליגי בסוכה גדולה *pligi be-sukkah ketana, pligi be-sukkah gedola*. They're debating a
big סוכה sukkah *sukkah* and a small סוכה sukkah *sukkah*, small and
a big. וחסורי מחסרא והכי קתני *ve-hisurei mechsara ve-hachi katani*. It must
be that some words are missing, and here's how it would have
to be taught. מי שהיה ראשו ורובו rosho verubo בסוכה ושולחנו בתוך
הבית *mi shehaya rosho ve-rubo ba-sukkah ve-shulchano betoch habayit*, somebody whose head
and body was in the סוכה sukkah. *sukkah* and his table was
in the house. So it's a big סוכה sukkah *sukkah*, but the
scenario is that the table's in the house. בית שמאי Beit Shammai
אומרים לא יצא lo yatza. *Beit Shammai omrim lo yatza*, בית שמאי
Beit Shammai *Beit Shammai* says you didn't fulfill your obligation. So now
we're inserting these words: לא יצא *lo yatza*, you didn't fulfill your
obligation. ובית הלל אומרים יצא *u-Beit Hillel omrim yatza*, and בית bayis,
הלל *Beit Hillel* says you did fulfill your obligation. That's one debate,
the scenario of a big סוכה sukkah *sukkah* but the table's in
the house. Now another case is the minimum size. ושאינה מחזקת אלא
כדי ראשו ורובו בלבד *ve-she'eina machzika ela kidei rosho ve-rubo bilvad*. What
about if it's a small size that can only contain your head
and your body? בית bayis, שמאי פוסלין *Beit Shammai poslin*, בית bayis.
שמאי *Beit Shammai* invalidate, ובית הלל מכשירין machshirin *u-Beit Hillel machshirin*, and
בית הלל *Beit Hillel* validate. So that's a second debate, not a
debate of a scenario of how you're eating, but a debate of
minimum size. And they actually debate both. So there's a few things
to point out. First of all, often when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says חסורי מחסרא *hisurei mechsara* or some words are missing, you know,
you're left with a feeling that that's a very forced read of
the original text. And some אחרונים *acharonim* say that, like the הגר"א
*Gra* explicitly says that when the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says חסורי מחסרא
*hisurei mechsara* it's just because the ברייתא *braita* doesn't or the text
doesn't fit with its position and therefore it's consciously, you know, changing
the text, it's not really claiming that there was a different גרסא
*girsa*. Here, though, it is somewhat persuasive because you do see that
there's two debates going on. There's evidence that there's a debate about
minimum size and the language of the משנה *Mishna*, as the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* points out, points both ways. On the one hand, the
משנה *Mishna* is talking about a scenario of the table being in
the house and on the other hand the language of פוסלין *poslin*
and מכשירין machshirin *machshirin* seem to be talking about the status of
the סוכה sukkah *sukkah*. So number one, it seems like actually here,
it's a very reasonable claim that this was somehow two debates that
got conflated into one text. Now, are these debates linked? Logically they
seem to be, right? They seem to be parallel. How would you
explain the linkage? So it seems that it's the following, that what
is considered to be a minimum size in order for to inhabit.
So what does inhabiting mean? We will find out later that inhabiting
means as we would say, what does it mean to live in
a סוכה sukkah *sukkah*? To eat. We'll find out later it also
means to sleep. Okay, but if it contains your head and most
of your body then you can sleep in it. You know, at
least your head won't get rained on or whatever. And presumably if
most of you is in it, it's considered like all of you
is in it. So you're sleeping in that... space, it's a minimum
size to just contain you to be, to be something to provide
shelter for sleeping, okay, because it's got the majority. Well, can it
also provide space for eating? So is it considered somewhat acceptable and
natural to be able to eat if you can't have your table
in there with you? So that's linked to this question of: are
we concerned you're going to follow after your table? Because בית שמאי
that says, I think that it's very hard for people to stay
in one space and their table to be somewhere else and then
to be, sort of, present in the place they're in, I don't
trust you to be able to do that. I think you'll naturally
be drawn after it. Well, if that's true, he can't consider a
space that doesn't allow for your table to be there to be
one that allows for natural habitation because there's no permanence there, you're
always being pulled out. Whereas בית הלל feels I'm not concerned you'll
be pulled after your table. I think you can get your food
and that you'll be able to root yourself in this place even
if your food is somewhere else. So according to him, even if
the space cannot contain your table, it's enough of a minimum space
to be some form of a habitation in some way in which
you can be present, you know, and inhabiting that space. So it
seems to be that that seems to be the explanation about how
the debates are linked. Now there's a fascinating question because we פסקן
paskin at least above like בית שמאי in terms of the minimum
size. Do we also פסקן pasken like בית שמאי in terms of
the question if you have a large סוכה sukkah and your table's
in the house? So that's actually a מחלוקת ראשונים. machlokes Rishonim. How
much do we really link the two debates? Okay? So a number
of ראשונים Rishonim פסקן paskin like בית שמאי for minimum size, but
they say if it's a big סוכה sukkah? and your table's in
the house, it's okay, you're still יוצא. yotzei. Others say no, no,
no, as we've been discussing, they logically come together. So part of
this תוספות Tosafot discusses that, and this תוספות Tosafot also discusses the
question about which are the times when we פסקן paskin like בית
שמאי because, you know, it's very rare that we פסקן pasken like
בית שמאי. So the beginning of the תוספות, Tosafot, if you just
look at the first line of the תוספות: Tosafot: תאמר לך מאני
בית שמאי היא ולא תזוז מינה. tama lach mani Beit Shammai hi
velo tazuz minah. He says: בסדר רב עמרם פסק בשישה מקומות הלכה
כבית שמאי חדא האי דסוכה צריכה שתהא מחזקת ראשו ורובו ושולחנו. beseder
Rav Amram pasak beshisha mekomot halacha keBeit Shammai chada hai deSukkah tzericha
shetehe machzeket rosho verubo veshulchano. So he quotes one of the גאונים
Geonim that says there are six places we פסקן paskin like בית
שמאי and this is one of them.
Dov, you had a question? Right, so in either of these two
debates, linked or unlinked, is the language of מכשירין and יוצא yotzei
בדיעבד bedieved or לכתחילה? lechatchila? And in general are those terms assumed
to be לכתחילה lechatchila positions? So מכשירין is not בדיעבד. bedieved. יוצא
yotzei is sometimes understood
to be בדיעבד, bedieved, sometimes not. It often might depend on context.
Right, like in שהכל נהיה בדברו shehakol nihiyeh bidvaro or something instead
of בורא פרי האדמה. borei peri ha-adamah. Right, yeah, sometimes יוצא yotzei
means בדיעבד bedieved but מכשירין generally means לכתחילה, lechatchila, yes. Now one
last thing I
do want to point out, which is this phrase that we saw
from the משנה over there,
where they said בית שמאי—what בית שמאי said to רבי יוחנן Rabbi
Yochanan was: כך היית נוהג לא קיימת מצוות סוכה מימיך. kach hayita
nohag lo kiyamta mitzvat Sukkah mi-yamecha. You've never fulfilled the מצוות סוכה
mitzvah of Sukkah in your life if you did this. Now what
do they mean by that? If he was sitting in a big
סוכה sukkah and his table was in the house, okay, he was
being עובר over on a דרבנן derabbanan stricture and maybe דרבנן derabbanan
לא יצא, you know, maybe דרבנן derabbanan you weren't יוצא, yotzei, but
what do you mean I didn't fulfill it? I mean, at least
מדאורייתא mi-d'Oraisa I was יוצא. yotzei. And this leads to a fascinating
question of: can the rabbis, you know, prevent you from being, make
a גזירה gezeirah or say something and prevent you from being יוצא
yotzei מדאורייתא mi-d'Oraisa when you really were יוצא yotzei מדאורייתא? mi-d'Oraisa? Now
they could always tell you you didn't הלכה halachically do your obligation
and you have to do it again at a דרבנן derabbanan level,
but does that really mean that when I die and go off
to heaven I won't have gotten credit for at least having done
it מדאורייתא? mi-d'Oraisa? So this also comes up at the very beginning
of ברכות Brachos where it
speaks about not saying שמע Shema after חצות, chatzos, right? If you
know that first משנה, you can really say שמע the whole night,
but don't say after חצות. chatzos. What happens if you said it
after חצות? chatzos? Are you יוצא yotzei or are you not יוצא?
yotzei? Since the only reason not to do it before midnight, I
mean, to do before midnight is דרבנן. derabbanan. Right. So there is—so
the גמרא actually brings in this משנה about סוכה sukkah, and eating
in the house and the upshot of that and the possibility of
being drawn after that and the language of לא קיימת מצוות סוכה
מימיך. lo kiyamta mitzvat Sukkah mi-yamecha. And the upshot of it is
distilled in the last few lines of this תוספות. Tosafot. So let's
take a look at this תוספות Tosafot דאמר de-amar and take a
look at what he says here. About ten lines before the lines
get wide, the lines start with the word ובית שמאי, uBeit Shammai,
you see that? Okay, so I'll go one line above that: היכא
דבית הלל מחמירין מדרבנן ובית שמאי מוקמי לדאורייתא. heicha deBeit Hillel machmirin
mid'rabbanan uBeit Shammai mokmi ledi-Oraisa. There was like a reverse case that
בית הלל was—I'm sorry, no, there was a reverse case that בית
הלל was the מחמירים machmirim and בית שמאי was not. ולא גזרינן.
velo gazrin. אי עשה כדברי בית שמאי. ee asa kedivrei Beit Shammai.
If you went like בית שמאי and you did the דאורייתא d'Oraisa
but you were not attending to the דרבנן derabbanan problem of בית
הלל, לא יצא. יצא ידי חובתו אפילו דאורייתא *yatza yedei chovaso afilu
d'Oraisa*. If you went against Beis Hillel's rabbinic problems, then you didn't
even fulfill the biblical obligation, כדאשכחן *k'da'ashkachan* like we find in the
reverse case by the סוכה sukkah, *sukkah* לבית שמאי *l'Beis Shammai* היכא
דיתיב אפיתחא דמטללתא *heicha deyisiv afischa d'matalaltah* דגזרי שמא ימשך אחר שולחנו
*degazri shema yimashach achar shulchano*. You're, you have a big סוכה sukkah?
*sukkah*, but your table's in the house, and we're afraid you'll go
after your table. דאמרי ליה בית שמאי לא קיימתם מצות סוכה sukkah
מימיכם *d'amri lei Beis Shammai lo kiyamtem mitzvas sukkah miyamechem* דאפילו מדאורייתא
לא קיים *d'afilu m'Oraisa lo kiyam*. That even biblically, once we rabbinically
tell you you can't do it, then even biblically you're not יוצא
*yotze* your obligation. Now what exactly are the mechanics that the rabbis
can say don't do it and not only are you being עובר
*over* on a דרבנן *d'rabbanan* but not being יוצא *yotze* in a
דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* is fascinating. Some want to say maybe it's מצוה הבאה
בעבירה *mitzvah haba'ah b'aveirah*, maybe it's יש כח ביד חכמים *yesh koach
beyad chachamim*, who knows what it is. But it's interesting because we're
much normally think of דרבנן *d'rabbanan* in the terms of in areas
of איסורים *issurim* and restrictions. Don't do the מלאכות *melachos* on שבת
*Shabbos* and don't do מוקצה *muktzah* and don't do a million other
דרבנן *d'rabbanan*s. So we know, what's the consequence of violating a דרבנן
*d'rabbanan*? It's a transgression, it's a rabbinic transgression. But what's the consequence
when דרבנן *d'rabbanan*s are in the world not of לא תעשה *lo
sa'asei*s but of מצות עשה *mitzvos asei* where they're telling you here's
how rabbinically we want you to do the מצוה *mitzvah* of סוכה
sukkah? *sukkah*. I didn't do that דרבנן *d'rabbanan*. So okay, did I
transgress? Maybe even I transgressed, but did I, but I still did
a מצוה *mitzvah*, I still did a מצות סוכה *mitzvas sukkah*. So
to what degree do the דרבנן *d'rabbanan*s when they're relating to מצות
עשה *mitzvos asei* and put additional requirements, do they actually limit your
ability to be יוצא *yotze*, not only on a rabbinic level but
even on a biblical level. So there is the possibility that it
could even be biblical based on how you read that סוגיא *sugya*
in סוכה *Sukkah*, it's not our immediate סוגיא *sugya*, but even if
you do say it sometimes happens, it doesn't mean it always happens.
Like you know there's a, there're going to be a lot of
דרבנן *d'rabbanan*s by סוכה *sukkah*. What's כשר סכך schach. דאורייתא *kosher s'chach
d'Oraisa*, what's כשר סכך schach דרבנן *kosher s'chach d'rabbanan*, what's dot dot
dot dot. It doesn't mean that every single one you would say
you're not יוצא *yotze* on a דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* level, but it does
put that possibility out there. Yes. And then there's my favorite example
of the possibility of redeeming מעשר שני *ma'aser sheini* on an אסימון
*asimon*. Yes. The rabbis seem to think that if you do that,
you have not... Okay, that's different. That's a question of rabbinic interpretation
of verses. That is a bit different than here. Here they're saying
that we, we acknowledge that biblically you're יוצא *yotze*, but we at
a rabbinic level, our, rabbinically our, legislating an additional requirement. So your
case is rabbinic interpretation, not legislation. That's a huge distinction. I would
say the same thing about מחיצה *mechitzah* and דם *dam*. Well, all
right, we're not going to go there, but okay. In other words,
I got it. מאן תנא *man tana*, back to the גמרא *Gemara*,
five, six lines from the bottom. מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן Rabbanan
*man tana l'ha d'sanu rabbanan*. So now, so that's number one, the
minimum size: ראשו ורובו *rosho v'rubo* or ראשו ורובו ושולחנו *rosho v'rubo
v'shulchano*, debate Beis Hillel, Beis Shammai. Now we're going to turn to
Rebbi's position that has a bigger minimum size: ארבע אמות amot על
ארבע אמות amot *arba amos al arba amos*. Okay. מאן תנא להא
דתנו רבנן Rabbanan *man tana l'ha d'sanu rabbanan*, who is the תנא
*tanna* of the following ברייתא *beraisa*: בית שאין בו ארבע אמות amot
על ארבע אמות amot *bayis she'ein bo arba amos al arba amos*,
if a house is less than four אמה amah *amah* by four
אמה amah *amah*. Basically the point of this ברייתא *beraisa* is going
to be that a house less than four אמות amot. *amos* by
four אמות amot *amos* does not constitute a house. That the ארבע
אמות amot על ארבע אמות amot, *arba amos al arba amos* is
the minimum size of a house for הלכות *halachos* that demand a
house. What type of הלכות *halachos* demand a house? So let's take
a look. If it doesn't have four אמות amot, *amos* by four
אמות amot, *amos*, פטור מן המזוזה *patur min hamuzuzah*, there's no obligation
of a מזוזה mzuza *mezuzah*, because it says על מזוזות ביתך mezuzot
beitecha *al mezuzos beisecha* ומן המעקה *u'min hama'akeh*, it doesn't need a
roof because it says כי תבנה בית חדש *ki sivneh bayis chadash*.
Okay, a house. Okay, not a roof, a railing around the roof.
ואינו מטמא בנגעים *v'eino mitamei binega'im*, if it gets spots it does
not become טמא *tamei* with נגעים *nega'im* because it says כנגע נראה
לי בבית *kenega nir'ah li babayis* ואינו נחלט בבתי ערי חומה v'eino
nechalit b'vatei arei chomah, *v'eino nechlat bevatei arei chomah*, if you sell
a house in a walled city, then at the end of a
year, you have a year to redeem it, at the end of
the year it permanently transfers over to the buyer. If it's not
four by four אמות amos. *amos*, it's not treated as a house,
it's treated just as like an open field, as a yard, and
therefore it could always be redeemed and it would go back ביובל
*b'Yovel*, not have any special those special rules. ואין חוזרים עליו מעורכי
המלחמה *v'ein chozrim alav me'orchei hamilchamah*, if you built a new house
but it was less than four אמות amos *amos* by four אמות
amos *amos*, then you would not be a basis of returning from
the battle, from you know from going out to war, it would
not be an exemption from the draft, because the exemption from the
draft is somebody אשר בנה בית חדש *asher banah bayis chadash*, who
built a house, and this isn't a house. ואין מערבין בו ואין
משתתפין בו *v'ein m'arvin bo v'ein mishtatfin bo*, if it is a
house in a courtyard, then it is not required to participate in
the עירוב eruv *eiruv*, and is not, you know, to give the
bread for the עירוב eruv *eiruv*. Or if the courtyards are getting
together for a שיתוף מבואות shituf mavo'os, *shituf mevo'os*, a joining of
the courtyards in an alleyway, and it is the only house of
a courtyard that opens up into the alleyway, then that courtyard does
not have to contribute the bread either because this is not a
house and the requirement is only for the houses to participate, or
courtyards that have houses. So if this is a courtyard and only
has this one structure, it doesn't have to participate because this does
not, does not constitute a house. ואין מניחין בו עירוב eiruv *v'ein
manichin bo eiruv*, similarly if the houses of the courtyard... yard all
got together to get this loaf of bread or these loaves of
bread, you can't store it in this house because it has to
be stored at a house and this isn't a house. ואין עושין
פה of ג' עמוד ב' Gimmel Amud Bet ואין עושין אותו עיבור
בין שתי עיירות Ve'ein osin oto ibur bein shtei ayarot also you
do not make it a pregnancy between two cities. What this means
is the following, okay, you might remember the idea that you have
2000 אמות amos of outside of city limits. Here's your city, okay,
and you have 2000 אמות amos as your תחום, techum, right, in
all directions. Now, let's say you've got another city over here. Okay,
you have two... let's not go there. Let's say you've got another
city over here. When are they considered to be one city and
you start the 2000 אמות amos. from the top here and from
the bottom here and it's all one big city, and when are
they considered two separate cities? Okay, so if they were within basically...
each city, the general rule is... here's another question, how far out
you've got some houses here, when are those houses considered... where do
you draw the city limits? And the basic rule is anything that
is within 70 and 2/3 אמה amah between one house and the
next, it's all considered connected. So if they're within 70 and 2/3
אמה they're all considered connected. Okay, so similarly, if let's say this
city was 70 and 2/3 אמה here, then of course it would
be one city. But let's say instead what you actually have is
that they're 141 and 1/3, meaning they're not 70 and 2/3 within
another. Okay, but they're 70 and 2/3 in the middle point. So
what would you need here in order to be able to daisy
chain and get it all to connect? A house! So if you
got a house here, this house then becomes part of this city,
it's within 70 and 2/3 and part of this city, and then
the cities are connected. So if you have a house, but it
has to be defined as a house, and if it's not a
house, it cannot serve to extend the city limits. Okay, so that's
the point of making it part of the pregnancy of the cities.
Okay, ואין עושין אותו עיבור בין שתי עיירות. Ve'ein osin oto ibur
bein shtei ayarot. ואין האחים והשותפים Ve'ein ha'achim vehashutfin and the brothers
who are also... ואין האחים והשותפים Ve'ein ha'achim vehashutfin normally is translated
as brothers who are partners, meaning when they're dividing an estate, but
whatever, brothers or sometimes it means brothers and poor partners... חולקין בו
cholkin bo you don't divide a house that's that small, right, you
take half of it, I take the other half, it's too small
to be divided. Now, the question is even if it was larger,
you know, you'd think each one would need to get 4x4. So
the גמרא will discuss the last case is a little complicated. So
let's take a look. So the גמרא says all these things you
see require 4x4 אמות amos. to define something as a house. לימא
רבי היא ולא רבנן Leima Rabbi hi velo Rabbanan this presumably is
the position of רבי Rabbi who his minimum size of a סוכה
is 4x4 אמות. amos, So the גמרא says no, אפילו תימא רבנן
Afilu teima Rabbanan even the רבנן Rabbanan could agree to that. עד
כאן לא קאמרי רבנן התם לענין סוכה דדירת עראי היא. Ad kan
lo kaamri Rabbanan hatam le'inyan sukkah d'dirat arai hi. The רבנן Rabbanan
only said that a סוכה which is a temporary dwelling can be
like, you know, seven טפחים, tefachim, can be ראשו ורובו ושלחנו. rosho
verubo veshulchano. Its whole definition is temporary. אבל לגבי בית Aval legabi
bayit things that require a house, דדירת קבע הוא d'dirat keva hu
a house is defined as... the whole difference of a house and
a סוכה is it's defined as a permanent dwelling. So therefore, אפילו
רבנן מודי afilu Rabbanan modi even the רבנן would agree דאי איכא
ארבע אמות על ארבע אמות דיירי אינשי d'ee ika arba amot al
arba amot dayri inshi 4x4 אמות amos, people will live, meaning they'll
live in a regular basis, not just as a temporary type of
living, but a more permanent way. ואי לא לא דיירי אינשי V'ee
lo lo dayri inshi unless it's 4x4 is not a place that
anybody would live in in an ongoing basis. So basically we have
introduced an important idea that 4x4 אמות amos presumably everybody agrees is
the minimum size for a דירת קבע dirat keva for a permanent
dwelling, which is the normal thing הלכה halacha cares about defining something
as a house. Okay, the smaller size ראשו ורובו ושלחנו rosho verubo
veshulchano is because of an idea that a סוכה is not defined
as a house. A סוכה is not defined as a permanent dwelling.
A סוכה is defined as a temporary dwelling and therefore can be
smaller, which raises the question of how does רבי Rabbi define a
סוכה. Because if רבי Rabbi says a סוכה has to be 4x4
אמות, amos, it sounds like רבי Rabbi would define a סוכה how?
As what type of a dwelling? A permanent, right? Maybe that's exactly
the debate. Maybe everybody agrees 4x4 is permanent and maybe ראשו ורובו
everybody should agree is a temporary dwelling. Maybe... and רבי Rabbi might
only demand 4x4 because maybe he thinks a סוכה also has to
have a status of a permanent dwelling. So this is a really
interesting question because when the מסכת masechet opened, we said that maybe
a סוכה has to be small enough in order not necessarily small
in dimensions but in height, but has to not be defined as
a permanent dwelling. Right? Now we're saying no, that actually the fact
that it's a temporary dwelling means that it's okay if it's smaller,
but there's no problem if it's bigger. Okay, so this is really,
you know, quite fascinating in terms of how do you define a
סוכה and we'll continue to, to work that through. Okay, but I
hope I'm being clear, meaning it's the idea permanent or temporary, right?
How do you define a סוכה? It could be עראי arai and
it could be קבע. keva. So first of all, do you say
the whole point of a סוכה is to be עראי arai different
from your house or no? Since you have to בסכות תשבו, basukkot
teshvu, you have to live in a סוכה, so if you've got
to live in a סוכה, so how do you live? You have
to live, it has to be habitable. So it has to be
permanent. Okay? So if you say it requires קבע, keva, it requires
קבע, keva, right? That might mean a minimum size. That could be
four by four אמות, maybe other things. Okay, we'll see. Okay, so
but that means that in order to do תשבו, teshvu, in order
to be like your house, okay, it has to have certain amount
of ways in which it has more permanence. Now עראי arai normally
could be interpreted two ways. Right? It could mean it must be
עראי, arai, must be, because the whole point here is it has
to be different from your house, it's not your house, it has
to be different from your house. And if you said must be
עראי, arai, you might demand that it actually be made in a
way that's more temporary. So what might that be? Maybe less than
twenty אמות, right? Now
nobody ever said it had to be small. Okay, but in theory
you could have said maybe it has to be small, right? Because
you're demanding. What did תוספות Tosafot say, what's one thing we started
today by reviewing, what did תוספות Tosafot say is demanded by the
idea of עראי? arai? What's demanded by the idea of עראי? arai?
We started, the one thing that can't be made in a permanent
way in your סוכה? The סכך. schach, Okay, the סכך schach cannot
be permanent.
Okay, cannot be permanent. However you define permanent, letting the rain be.
So that's a way in which
it requires, it requires עראי. arai. But other aspects like the question
here of the dimensions of the seven טפחים tfachim by seven טפחים,
tfachim, right? Nobody, nobody says that it has to be small. Where
are the areas that we require עראי, arai, you know, is not,
you know, is to be figured out. Okay, and but regarding the,
so maybe it requires it by the סכך, but regarding the issue
of the minimum seven by seven טפחים, tfachim, we're not saying it
has to be small, we're saying it's okay if it's עראי. arai.
But then you have a principle that עשות סוכתו קבע וביתך עראי.
asot sukkato keva u'veitcha arai. Right, I understand. That's their debate. רבי
Rebbi says
in order for it to serve as your house it has to
be קבע. keva. רבנן say in order for it not to be
your house, it's got to be עראי. arai. But again, that doesn't
demand that everything be עראי. arai. Maybe minimally it demands that the
סכך be עראי. arai. But in terms of the size, we're saying
it's okay if it's עראי. arai.
Yeah, no it's really, it is interesting because that concept of transferring
from your house to the סוכה as the place that's קבע, keva,
right,
is it located in the demands of the physical structure, right? Or
is it in your perception of what you're doing?
Right. Right. So okay, so this is important and we'll get back
to it. But here we are seeing that everybody agrees that four
by four is the size of a house. The question is what
is it that you demand of a סוכה? Okay, so אמר מר,
פטור מן המזוזה ומן המעקה. patur min hamzuza u'min hamaka. Now we're
going to unpack this. It's exempt from מזוזה and from a railing.
ואין מטמא בנגעים v'ein metamei b'negaim and from צרעת. tzaraat. ואינו נחלט
בבתי ערי חומה, it doesn't get sold in the city, it doesn't
get, you know, the sale isn't made
irreversible after a year. ואין חוזרים עליו מערכי המלחמה, v'ein chozrim alav
me'orchei hamilchama, you don't go back from the draft. מאי טעמא? mai
ta'ama? Why? דבית כתיב הוא בכולהו, d'bayis ktiv hu b'chulu, all of
them it says בית as I mentioned when we were doing it
the first time. All the verses, it says מזוזות ביתך
and בית, בית, בית. And everybody agrees you need four by four
to be considered a house. ואין מערבין בו ואין משתתפין בו ואין
מניחין בו עירוב. v'ein me'arvin bo v'ein mishtatfin bo v'ein manichin bo
eruv. You don't, it doesn't have to participate in עירוב eiruv and
you can't put an עירוב eiruv in it. מאי טעמא? mai ta'ama?
דלא חזי לדירה, d'lo chazi l'dira, it's not fit for dwelling. So
even though there's no conceptual idea of house, but the idea still
is the people that dwell in the courtyard have to join together
for it to be one space, right? So therefore it has to
be, you have to be considered to dwell there. And if you
live in a little hut that's small by four by four, you're
just passing through, you're not really dwelling there. Okay, but it's not
as much about the object of the house. There's no concept of
an object of the house. עירובי חצרות אין מניחין בו. eruvei chatzeirot
ein manichin bo. Now it clarifies. You don't put the עירוב eiruv
that's made by the houses of the courtyard in it because the
הלכה halacha is where does the עירוב eiruv. go? It goes into
one of the houses and we just said this isn't a house
or this isn't a place, a space that's part of that arrangement.
אבל שיתוף מניחין בו, Aval shituf manichin bo,
you can put the bread collected for the שיתוף מבואות, shituf mavo'os
for the courtyard getting together to join in in a shared alleyway.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? דלא גרע מחצר. Delo gara michatzer. It's no
worse than the courtyard itself. The הלכה halacha is שחצר במבוי, shechatzer
bamavoi, that's in the מבוי. mavoi. Now, people remember like the basic
configuration here? Yes, right? Houses in are part of a חצר, chatzer,
and
the חצירות chatzeiros
open up into a מבוי. mavoi.
So, where do you put when you join together in a חצר
chatzer all the houses going together, you put the עירוב eiruv in
one of the houses of the חצר? chatzer? And this isn't a
house. When all the חצירות chatzeiros join together in order to be
able to use the מבוי, mavoi, where does it go? It goes
in the חצר. chatzer. It could go in the חצר. chatzer. It
doesn't have to go in a house; it go actually in the
yard itself as long as it's in a protected space. דתנן, Detnan,
we taught in the משנה: עירובי חצרות
בחצר ושיתופי מבואות במבוי. Eiruvi chatzeiros bachatzer v'shitufai mavo'os bamavoi. And the
שיתוף מבואות shituf mavo'os. goes in the מבוי. mavoi. Now, that's not
true. והוינא בה, V'havinan bah, we asked on this: עירובי חצרות בחצר?
Eiruvi chatzeiros bachatzer? You עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros
goes in the yard itself? והתניא, Vehatanya, but it says in the
ברייתא: הנותן עירובו בבית שער אכסדרה ומרפסת, Hanosein eiruvo b'veis sha'ar achsadra
u'mirpeses, if you put your עירוב in the, like, a gatehouse, the
little hut that the guard sits in by the gate, or the
אכסדרה, achsadra, the
portico. If you look at רש"י Rashi about eight lines down in
the medium-sized lines, אכסדרה, achsadra, רש"י Rashi says: שלפני הבית שקורין פורטיק"ו.
shelifnei habayis shekorin portico. So
just let you appreciate that, okay? Right. Yeah, a vestibule, or it's
also something that's sometimes be roofed and like have columns that hold
it up. Okay. ומרפסת, U'mirpeses, or a, you know, a porch. אינו
עירוב, Eino eiruv, it's not good, because it has to be in
a place that people dwell, and people go pass through these places;
they don't dwell in those places. שהדר שם אינו אוסר, Shehadar sham
eino oser, and if you live there, you don't make a problem
for other people; you don't have to contribute to the עירוב. That's
not a place that it's considered to be a place where you
dwell. So you don't just put the עירוב in the yard; you've
got to put it in one of the houses. אלא אימא, Ela
eima, here's how you have to read the משנה: עירובי חצרות בבית
שבחצר. Eiruvi chatzeiros b'bayis shebachatzer. The עירוב חצרות eiruv chatzeiros goes
in one of the houses of the courtyard. ושיתופי מבואות בחצר שבמבוי.
V'shitufai mavo'os bachatzer shebamavoi. And the
partnership for the מבוי, mavoi, for the alleyway,
goes into one of the yards of the מבוי. mavoi. So since
that can go in the yard, when it's for the it can't
for the חצר, chatzer, it has to the עירובי חצרות, eiruvi chatzeiros,
it has to go in a house; it is in a house.
But for the for the unifying of the alleyway, it goes in
a yard. So a yard it can also go into this little
hut. So therefore
והאי לא גרע מחצר שבמבוי, vehai lo gara michatzer shebamavoi, this little
hut is no worse than putting it literally in the courtyard itself.
That's that explanation. So it's only it's only a problem of putting
it in for the עירוב חצרות, eiruv chatzeiros, not for the שיתוף
מבואות. Now the last part, the last two parts: ואין עושין אותו
עיבור בין שתי העיירות. Ve'ein osin oso ibur bein shtei ha'ayaros. It's
not a pregnancy between these two cities as we described. דאפילו כבורגנין
לא משוינן לה. De'afilu k'burganin lo mshavinan lah.
It's not even like a בורגנין, burganin, which is like a little
lean-to that's made for watching the field. So the interesting point here
is, is that the, what do you call it, the this case
about the two cities, right? And this thing here that's in the
midpoint, it doesn't have to be a house. Even if it's a
lean-to that somebody goes to watch the sheep in the fields, that
can connect it. So if you can connect it by a lean-to,
why do you need a four by four house? So, so here's
the answer. It says like this: מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? בורגנין חזו
למילתייהו. Burganin chazu l'milsaihu.
Because something that's a lean-to is fit for what it's made for.
והאי לא חזי למילתיה. Vehai lo chazi l'milsai. This is constructed like
a house, but it's not fit for living. This is like a,
there's basically it's like a difference, there's a difference between a condemned
house and a tent. Okay? Does a condemned house provide the same
amount of shelter as a tent? Maybe. But if it's a condemned
house, it has no it's not recognized as having any, like, you
know, it's inappropriate, nobody would live here in this context because it's
too of a house and it's not fit for living as a
house, as opposed to something that's built as a tent, that actually
suffices. So while you don't need a house here, but if it's
made as a house and it's too small, that makes it illegitimate.
Okay? רש"י, Rashi, by the way, points out that a בורגנין burganin
is made for like one night's sleep, whereas something that's constructed as
a house is implicitly made for multiple nights and for more regular
dwelling, and this is not fit for that. So that's why it
does not join the two cities. And the last point is: ואין
אחין ושותפין חולקין בו. Ve'ein achin u'shutfinn cholkin bo. You cannot divide
a house this small. So the גמרא says one minute. טעמא דלית
ביה ארבע אמות, ta'ama d'leit bei arba amos, you're telling me that
you can't divide it because it's not four אמות. הא אית ביה
ארבע אמות חולקין? hai it bei arba amos cholkin? Once it's four
אמות by four אמות you can divide it? How is a house
four אמות by four אמות fit to be divided? והתנן, v'hatnan, ותנן
במשנה, u'tanan bamishna, אין חולקין את החצר עד שיהא בו ארבע אמות
לזה וארבע אמות לזה. ein cholkin es hachatzer ad sheyehei bo arba
amos l'zeh v'arba amos l'zeh. You don't, you can't divide a courtyard
until each person can get four by four אמות. And if no,
and in that case it can't be, so maybe you sell it
and divide the proceeds, but it's not considered that somebody is getting
anything meaningful if you're giving them less than four by four אמות.
So even if it is four by four אמות, you can't divide
it. Each person doesn't get enough? So the גמרא says אלא אימא
אין בו דין חלוקה כחצר. ella eima ein bo din chalukah k'chatzer.
It doesn't get divided like a חצר chatzer gets divided. What does
that mean? And now we're going to see that the way you
divide a חצר chatzer is somewhat determined by the number of houses
in the courtyard. So let's take a look. דאמר רב הונא, d'amar
Rav Huna, חצר לפי פתחיה מתחלקת. chatzer l'fi pesachim mischalekes. A חצר
chatzer is divided by its doorways, ורב חסדא אמר, v'Rav Chisda amar,
נותן לכל פתח ופתח ארבע אמות, nosin l'chol pesach u'pesach arba amos,
every doorway gets four אמות, והשאר חולקין אותו בשוה, v'hashar chokin oso
b'shaveh, and everything else is divided equally. What does that mean? It
means two brothers, ראובן Reuven and שמעון, Shimon, are dividing the courtyard
that their father יעקב Yaakov left to them when he died. Okay,
now this courtyard had one nice big mansion over here, okay, and
it's got three little houses, three tiny little
houses here.
Okay, so ראובן Reuven says, and each one has one door. So
ראובן Reuven says I want the mansion, and שמעון Shimon
says I'm going to take the little houses. How do you divide
the courtyard? Okay, so one opinion says look, a courtyard, the whole
purpose of the yard is made to give you access into the
doors to unload your stuff and to, you know, go with your
donkeys and it all just serves the house. So one opinion says
שמעון Shimon gets has three doors and ראובן Reuven only has one
door, שמעון Shimon gets three-quarters of it and ראובן Reuven gets one-quarter.
Okay, they divide the courtyard based on the number of doors. The
other one says no, no, no, you need, I agree you need
some of this yard to serve the houses but not the whole
thing. So for each doorway you get four by four, you know,
or actually not four by four, four base times the length of
the doorway. Okay, but anyway you get you get a section of
four אמות by each doorway. That, you know, ראובן Reuven gets one
and שמעון Shimon gets three, but the rest is divided the rest
is divided equally. So here the point is if one of שמעון's
Shimon houses here is less than four by four, then it doesn't
count. However you you factor in the doorways, whether it's proportional the
whole yard
or whether it's to give you space in front of the doorway,
if your house is less than four by four it does not
it does not factor in. Okay, so let's just read that. דהני
מילי בית, dahani milei bayis, when do you factor in doorways, when
is it a doorway of a house דלמיהוי קאי, d'leimeha vei kai,
that it's going to stay that way, so יהבינן ליה, yahavinan leh,
so then we give you the appropriate amount, either the whole field
or four אמות, חצר chatzer דיהבינן ליה חצר d'yahavinan leh chatzer we
give you a portion of this yard. הי, hai, this, דלמיסתר קאי,
d'limistar kai, it's like I said a condemned house, it's ready it's
basically deserving to be knocked down, לא יהבינן ליה חצר lo yahavinan
leh chatzer you don't get any part of the yard that corresponds
to it because it has no significance, something that's made as a
house like this. Okay, and more of this.